Finding Aid for Toward A Fair Michigan records, 2005-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Toward A Fair Michigan records 2005-2008
Toward A Fair Michigan (Organization)
10.6 GB
1 linear foot
2009043 Bj 2
501(c)(3) nonprofit educational organization formed in February 2005 to open dialogue and increase citizen participation in the debate surrounding Proposal 2, the ballot initiative that ended affirmative action programs in Michigan and was passed in November 2006; records include correspondence, press coverage, organizational files, and materials relating to public events.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor no. 10066 ) was donated by Toward A Fair Michigan on November 18, 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Toward A Fair Michigan (TAFM) was a 501(c)(3) nonprofit educational organization formed in February 2005 in the midst of growing public debate around Proposal 2, a ballot initiative which sought to ban affirmative action and the use of preferences in decisions regarding public employment, education, and contracting. Based in East Lansing, TAFM was co-founded by Dr. William Barclay Allen, former Commissioner of the U.S. Civil Rights Commission, and Barbara Grutter, lead plaintiff in the 2003 U.S. Supreme Court case (Grutter v. Bollinger) which upheld the University of Michigan Law School's use of affirmative action in its admissions policy.
While both Grutter and Allen favored the enactment of Proposal 2, TAFM sought to rise above partisan politics and further the public's understanding of equal opportunity issues in Michigan by promoting a civil and open exchange of views on affirmative action. To this end, TAFM organized a series of public forums leading up to November 2006 in which proponents and opponents of Proposal 2 debated the important legal and social issues at stake in the election. Other TAFM activities included filing an amicus brief to support the ballot initiative process, publication of resource and reference materials related to affirmative action preferences, and production of the video documentary "Where Do You Stand?"
Following the passage of Proposal 2, TAFM adopted a new programmatic focus with the launch of ANCORE ("A New Conversation on Race and Ethnicity"). In this phase, TAFM also sought to publicize and promote steps taken to implement Proposal 2 and encourage state and local governments to adhere to the letter and spirit of the 2006 election decision. To accomplish these goals, the group conducted a survey of affirmative action-based discrimination in Michigan, monitored compliance with the new amendment, and unsuccessfully petitioned the U.S. District Court to block a constitutional challenge to Proposal 2. In an effort spearheaded by Carol Allen, TAFM also compiled and wrote Ending Racial Preferences: The Michigan Story (2008), an account of its genesis and the struggle against affirmative action preferences in Michigan and other states where similar initiatives have been passed. On October 22, 2008, the TAFM board voted to dissolve the corporation and transfer its financial assets to the Center for Individual Rights.
The Toward A Fair Michigan records reflect that organization's efforts to promote dialogue on the controversial ballot initiative Proposal 2 (the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative) and encourage public participation in the political process. In addition to illustrating essential steps in the formation and management of 501©(3) nonprofit groups, the records will be especially valuable to those interested in the public debate surrounding Proposal 2 and the issue of affirmative action in the United States in the early 21st century. The collection is comprised of three series: Administrative Files, Program Director's Files, and Organizational Activities.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan.; Constitutional amendments--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--2006.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.; Political campaigns--Michigan.; Toward A Fair Michigan (Organization)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan.; Constitutional amendments--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--2006.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.; Political campaigns--Michigan.; Toward A Fair Michigan (Organization)
Contributors:
Allen, W. B. (William Barclay) 1944-; Barnhizer, Daniel D.; Cohen, Carl, 1931-; Grutter, Barbara.; Sedler, Robert Allen.; Weisskopf, Thomas E.
Genre Terms:
Websites.
- Administrative Files
  The Toward A Fair Michigan records reflect that organization's efforts to promote dialogue on the controversial ballot initiative Proposal 2 (the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative) and encourage public participation in the political process. In addition to illustrating essential steps in the formation and management of 501(c)(3) nonprofit groups, the records will be especially valuable to those interested in the public debate surrounding Proposal 2 and the issue of affirmative action in the United States in the early 21st century. The collection is comprised of three series: Administrative Files, Program Director's Files, and Organizational Activities.
  - Articles of Incorporation and Additional Registration 2005 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors 2005 (Box 1)
  - Business Plan 2005 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 2005 (Box 1)
  - Conflict of Interest Policy 2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 2005-2006, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Employer Identification Number 2005 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising Materials 2005 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - February 11, 2005 (Box 1)
    - March 4, 2005 (Box 1)
    - August 10, 2005 (Box 1)
    - December 16, 2005 (Box 1)
    - March 24, 2006 (Box 1)
    - June 21, 2006 (Box 1)
    - October 22, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Press File 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Ask the Experts!Questions from TAFM Debates, 2006 (Box 1)
    - "Creating the Civic Forum to Discuss Affirmative Action Preferences" brochure, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Discussion Guide circa 2006 (Box 1)
  - Reports 2006-2007, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Video Documentary
    - Broadcast Schedule and Correspondence 2006 (Box 1)
    - Where Do You Stand?, 2006, MPEG-4 video
  - Web Site (http://www.towardafairmichigan.org) 2008, PDF file
    (Captured on August 14, 2008)
- Program Director's Files
  The Program Director's Files series is comprised of born-digital records created and maintained by TAFM Program Director Carol Allan and includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, press releases, organizational bylaws, and logistical information for public events. The series also features audio and video recordings of public forums on the Michigan Civil Rights Initiative. This series contains materials related to the other two series in the collection.
  - Board 2006, ZIP archive file
  - Correspondence 2006, ZIP archive file
  - Leadership Assembly 2006, ZIP archive file
  - Litigation 2006, ZIP archive file
  - Organizational Documents 2005, ZIP archive file
  - Press 2005-2007, ZIP archive file
  - Programs
    - Audio files
      - Benton Harbor debate 2006, ZIP archive file
      - Ellis Cose Colloquium 2006, ZIP archive file
      - Grosse Pointe Unitarian debate 2006, ZIP archive file
      - Mackinac Center-Lansing debate 2005, ZIP archive file
      - Michigan Black Republican Council talk 2005, ZIP archive file
      - Union Missionary Baptist Church debate 2006, ZIP archive file
      - Wayne State University debate and summation 2006, ZIP archive file
    - Correspondence, advertisements and logistics 2005-2006, ZIP archive file
  - Publications circa 2005-2006, ZIP archive file
  - Speakers 2005-2006, ZIP archive file
  - Video (correspondence and other records related to broadcasts of Where Do You Stand?), 2006, ZIP archive file
- Organizational Activities
  The Organizational Activities series documents TAFM's work to present Michiganders with opposing arguments on affirmative action and advance its larger mission of expanding the public's well-informed participation in politics. It contains materials relating to TAFM presentations, the ANCORE ("A New Conversation On Racial Equality") leadership assembly, and the 2007 TAFM affirmative action survey. The largest portion of the series consists of publicity materials, correspondence, and position papers (as well as three DVD recordings) from the series of public forums TAFM sponsored in the run-up to the November 2006 vote on Proposal 2.
  - Affirmative Action Survey 2007 (Box 1)
  - ANCORE Leadership Assembly 2006 (Box 1)
  - Mackinac Republican Leadership Conference 2005 (Box 1)
  - Presentation for the Livonia Grumpies 2006 (Box 1)
  - Public Forums
    - "A Spirited Discussion on Affirmative Action," 2006 (Box 1)
    - Bay de Noc Community College 2006 (Box 1)
    - Central Michigan University's Griffin Policy Forum: "Affirmative Action/Racial Preferences: Should They Be Banned?" 2006
      - Event records (Box 1)
      - Video recording, MPEG-4 video file
    - Eastern Michigan University 2006 (Box 1)
    - East Lansing: "Should a Free Society Allow Affirmative Action Preferences in Higher Education?" 2005
      - Event records (Box 1)
      - Video recording, MPEG-4 video file
    - Flint 2006 (Box 1)
    - Grand Valley State University Affirmative Action Debate 2006
      - Event records (Box 1)
      - Video recording, MPEG-4 video file
    - Grosse Pointe 2006 (Box 1)
    - Lake Michigan Community College 2006 (Box 1)
    - Lansing: "The Economics of Affirmative Action" 2005
      - Event records (Box 1)
      - Video recording, MPEG-4 video file
    - Lansing 2006 (Box 1)
    - Livonia 2006 (Box 1)
    - Madison Heights 2006 (Box 1)
    - Northern Michigan University 2006 (Box 1)
    - Northwood University 2006 (Box 1)
    - Oakland University 2006 (Box 1)
      (includes invitations for U.S. Senate candidates to participate)
    - Traverse City (Michigan Chamber Foundation) 2005 (Box 1)
    - Wayne State University 2006 (Box 1)
    - Program Evaluations 2005-2006 (Box 1)
    - Speaker Contacts and Response Forms 2005-2006 (Box 1)